<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Karn Wong</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Karn Wong</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>แทคติคสอบถามโรงงานเรื่องกลูเตน</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-08-15-%E0%B9%81%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%B4%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%AA%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%9A%E0%B8%96%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A1%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%B7%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A5%E0%B8%B9%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%99/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-08-15-%E0%B9%81%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%B4%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%AA%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%9A%E0%B8%96%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A1%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%B7%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A5%E0%B8%B9%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%99/</guid>
      <description>มนุษย์ทุกคนต้องการอาหาร ไม่งั้นก็อยู่ไม่ได้เพราะหิวตายไปก่อน แต่ก็จะมีคนบางกลุ่มที่กินอาหารบางอย่างไม่ได้ อันนี้ก็ถือว่าเป็นความเคราะห์ร้ายไป แต่นั่นไม่ได้แปลว่า วงการอาหารควรจะนอนนิ่งเฉย เพราะบทคนกินอาหารบางอย่างไม่ได้ ไม่ใช่ว่าเขาเลือกที่จะไม่กิน แต่เขากินไม่ได้ จะตอบแบบกำปั้นทุบดินว่าจริงๆ แล้วกินได้ก็ใช่ แต่กินแล้วจะผื่นขึ้น ลำคอตีบ ปากบวม ท้องเสีย อะไรก็ว่าไป ซึ่งอาการไม่พึงประสงค์เหล่านี่ไม่ควรเกิดขึ้น
ตัวอาหารที่บางคนกินไม่ได้อาจจะเป็นตัวที่คนกินไม่ได้กันเยอะ อันนี้ก็ถือว่าโชคดี เพราะนั่นแปลว่าผู้ผลิตส่วนใหญ่จะแจ้งไว้บนฉลาก เช่น ไข่ นม แต่ ถ้าดันงอแงกับตัวแปลกๆ ที่คนไม่ค่อยรู้จักกัน อันนี้เริ่มจะอยู่ยาก บุฟเฟ่ร้านดัง อาหารร้านเด็ด โบกมือลาได้เลย
แล้วกลูเตนเกี่ยวอะไรด้วย? ความงอแงของคนที่กินกลูเตนไม่ได้ คือ ตัวนี้ผู้ประกอบการไม่ค่อยรู้จักกันว่ามันคืออะไร ต่อให้รู้จักก็ไม่ค่อยรู้อีกว่ามันจะไปอยู่ตรงไหนบ้าง ตามตำราก็จะบอกว่า กลูเตนเจอได้ในข้าวสาลี ไรย์ บาเลย์ มอลต์ แต่อันนี้มันเป็นต้นตอไง พอเข้าสู่กระบวนการผลิตมันไปกระจายทิ้งได้หลายจุดมาก เช่น ถ้าเป็นถั่ว บางทีตอนขนส่งเขาให้อุปกรณ์ร่วมกับการขนส่งข้าวสาลี ละอองข้าวสาลีติดถั่ว = ปนเปื้อนกลูเตน
บางคนอาจจะมีคำถามว่า ซีเรียสไปรึเปล่า แค่นี้เองก็กินไม่ได้เหรอ ก็จะขอตอบว่า คนที่ไม่กินกลูเต็นมีอยู่สามประเภทหลักๆ คือ คนที่แพ้แป้งสาลี คนที่ย่อยกลูเตนไม่ได้ และ คนที่ร่างกายเข้าใจว่ากลูเตนเป็นสิ่งแปลกปลอม เลยต้องกำจัดทิ้ง (celiac) &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; ลำไส้โดนกัด ทีนี้ คนที่แพ้แป้งสาลี อาการก็จะเหมือนคนที่แพ้กุ้ง ปลา ที่อาจจะทนปริมาณน้อยๆ ได้ เช่นเดียวกับคนที่ย่อยกลูเตนไม่ได้ แต่มนุษย์ celiac นั้น กลูเตนน้อยแค่ไหนก็เจ็บตัว</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impute pipelines</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-05-23-impute-pipelines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-05-23-impute-pipelines/</guid>
      <description>Imagine having a dataset that you need to use for training a prediction model, but some of the features are missing. The good news is you don&amp;rsquo;t need to throw some data away, just have to impute them. Below are steps you can take in order to create an imputation pipeline. Github link here!
from random import randint import pandas as pd import numpy as np from sklearn.preprocessing import OneHotEncoder from sklearn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Word-based analysis with song lyrics</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-04-16-word-based-analysis-with-song-lyrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-04-16-word-based-analysis-with-song-lyrics/</guid>
      <description>I listen to a lot of music, mostly symphonic heavy metal. What&amp;rsquo;s interesting is that in this genre, each album often has different themes, also each band focus on different topics in terms of lyrics. For instance, Nightwish focuses on nature, and their Imaginaerum album focuses on evolution. So I thought it would be interesting if I apply various text analysis methods to the lyrics, which resulted in this article. Github link here!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>อยู่เมืองไทยกินกลูเตนไม่ได้ช่างลำบาก</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-01-27-%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%A2%E0%B8%B9%E0%B9%88%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%B7%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%A2%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%B4%E0%B8%99%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A5%E0%B8%B9%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%A1%E0%B9%88%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%94%E0%B9%89%E0%B8%8A%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%A5%E0%B8%B3%E0%B8%9A%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%81/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-01-27-%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%A2%E0%B8%B9%E0%B9%88%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%B7%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%A2%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%B4%E0%B8%99%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A5%E0%B8%B9%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%A1%E0%B9%88%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%94%E0%B9%89%E0%B8%8A%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%A5%E0%B8%B3%E0%B8%9A%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%81/</guid>
      <description>เดี๋ยวนี้หันไปทางไหนก็เห็นแต่กระแสกลูเต็นฟรี นี่มองละเบะปากเพราะเกือบทั้งหมดฉันกินไม่ได้ จะไปกินได้ยังไงในเมื่อพวกนี้มันกะอัพราคากับมนุษย์ที่หลงกระแส ไม่ได้ทำมาให้พวกคนที่กินกลูเตนไม่ได้จริงๆ กิน
แล้วอย่าคิดว่าอ่านฉลากดีๆ แล้วจะรอด เพราะฉลากอาหารไทยนั้นลึก ลึกมากจนฉันเข้าไม่ถึง ตัวอย่างเบาะๆ ก็เช่น:
 หมูหมักซีอิ้ว แจ้งแค่ว่ามีถั่วเหลือง (ซีอิ้วหมักกับแป้งสาลี) ฉลากแปะช็อคโกแลตนำเข้า ที่ฉลากต้นทางเขียนว่ามีสารก่อภูมิแพ้สี่ห้าอย่างได้ ฉลากไทยเขียนแค่สอง และแน่นอนว่ากลูเตนไม่ค่อยโผล่ในฉลากไทย ต่อให้ฉลากต้นทางมันจะเขียนตัวหนามาก็ตาม  ที่ลำไยกว่าคือ ครั้นจะโทรถามโรงงานผลิตนี่ก็ต้องมาลุ้นอีกว่าเค้าจะรู้งานดีแค่ไหน บางทีแจ็คพอตพนักงานมีคุณภาพก็รอดไป แต่ส่วนใหญ่เจอน้อย ส่วนมากจะตอบแบบขอไปที ตอบแบบส่งๆ หรือไม่โทรกลับเลยก้มี (และแน่นอนว่าฉันจดชื่อบริษัทขึ้นบัญชีหนังหมาไว้แล้ว)
ที่เจอสดๆ วันนี้เลยก็คือ โทรไปถามโรงงานปลากระป๋องว่า ฉลากแจ้งกลูเตนสองระดับมั้ย ระดับแรกคือ ใส่ส่วนผสมนี้ลงไปในผลิตภัณฑ์จริงๆ ระดับสองคือ อาจจะมีส่วนผสมของ&amp;hellip;. มาจากการะบวนการผลิตที่ใช้อุปกรณ์ร่วมกัน ที่ถามแบบนี้เพราะว่า การแจ้ง &amp;ldquo;อาจจะมีส่วนผสมของ&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; ไม่ได้ทำกันทุกที่ และต่อให้ทำก็ใช่ว่าจะแจ้งกลูเตนกัน
มันพีคตรงที่พอพนง.ฟังแล้วก็บอกเลยว่า ผลิตภัณฑ์เราไม่มีกลูเตนเลย ในใจนี่เริ่มเดือดละ วันก่อนเห็นเต็มสองตาว่ามีทูน่าหมักซีอิ๊วญี่ปุ่น ฉลากแจ้งด้วยนะว่ามีแป้งสาลี อ่ะนี่ก็บอกให้ทางนั้นไปเช็คมา
สามชั่วโมงผ่านไป พนง.โทรกลับมาแจ้งว่า ทางบริษัทมีการแจ้งกลูเตนจากโชยุ แต่ประทานโทษ นั่นไม่ใช่คำถามฉัน นี่ต้องจี้แล้วจี้อีก ทางนั้นบทจะหนีก็ไล่ให้ไปอ่านฉลาก ถ้าอ่านมาจนถึงตรงนี้คิดว่าหลายๆ คนคงดูออกว่า ถ้าฉลากมันเชื่อถือได้ฉันคงไม่เสียค่าโทรศัพท์นั่งโทรถามหรอก เปลืองตังแถมเสียเวลาอีก สุดท้ายเลยจี้ถามว่า ถ้ามีผลิตภัณฑ์ ก ที่มีกลูเตน และผลิตภัณฑ์ ข ที่ไม่มีกลูเตน แต่ใช้สายผลิตร่วมกัน มีการตรวจสอบปริมาณกลูเตนตกค้างมั้ยว่าเจอเท่าไหร่ ทางนั้นก็ไปให้คนอ่านกล่องตัวทดสอบกลูเตนมา สรุปว่าฉันกินได้อย่างสบายใจถ้าไม่เจอคำว่า กลูเตน หรือ แป้งสาลีบนฉลาก</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My diet is not for you to market it as healthy</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-01-12-my-diet-is-not-for-you-to-market-it-as-healthy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-01-12-my-diet-is-not-for-you-to-market-it-as-healthy/</guid>
      <description>Assuming you&amp;rsquo;re from the Anglosphere or live in trendy neighborhoods, you will see a lot of places offering gluten-free options and slapping &amp;ldquo;healthy&amp;rdquo; label on it. The problem arises when restauraners see the opportunity to cash in the gluten-free wave and start offering gluten-free options. This is an issue because, gluten-free is not just eliminating wheat, barley, rye or oat. It&amp;rsquo;s more than that.
If you bake pizza using gluten-free flour in the same oven as regular pizza, it is considered cross-contaminated from floating flour dust in the air and some flour bits sticking to the oven, meaning it would contain gluten even if you use gluten-free flour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ความน่าปวดหัวของการถอดอักษรไทยเป็นตัวโรมัน</title>
      <link>/posts/2020-01-07-%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%9B%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%94%E0%B8%AB%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%82%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%96%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%94%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A9%E0%B8%A3%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%A2%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%9B%E0%B9%87%E0%B8%99%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%A7%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%99/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2020-01-07-%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%9B%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%94%E0%B8%AB%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%82%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%96%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%94%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A9%E0%B8%A3%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%A2%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%9B%E0%B9%87%E0%B8%99%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%A7%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%99/</guid>
      <description>English Version
*ตัวโรมัน = a b c d e f g &amp;hellip;
วันดีคืนดีชาวต่างชาติอยากมาเมืองไทย แต่จะมาเพราะอะไรนี่ก็ไม่ขอยุ่ง ไม่ได้สู่รู้เบอร์นั้น อนุมานว่ามาจากแถบยุโรป อเมริกาอะไรเทือกนี้ก็น่าจะเครื่องลงที่สุวรรณภูมิ ปัญหาที่จะเจออย่างแรกเลยก็คือ ชื่อป้ายชื่ออะไรไม่ได้ออกเสียงเหมือนที่ตัวโรมันเขียนไว้ เรื่องของเรื่องคือป้ายชื่อในไทยจะใช้ระบบ Royal Thai General System of Transcription ของ ราชบัณฑิตยสถาน แล้วปัญหาหลักๆ เลยก็คือมันไม่ได้สื่อว่าจริงๆ แล้วคำมันควรออกเสียงยังไง เช่น:
   Thai Romanization Romanization System Pronunciation Source     เทเวศ The-wet RTGS Tae-wet Pali-Sanskrit   สุวรรณภูมิ Suvarnabhumi Devanagari transliteration Su-wan*-na-poom *&amp;lsquo;a&amp;rsquo; as in father Pali-Sanskrit   ดินแดง Din-daeng RTGS Din-daeng Thai   ศรีราชา Sri Racha Mixed:__Sri__ - Devanagari transliteration__Racha__ - RTGS See-ra-cha Pali-Sanskrit    จะเห็นได้ว่าคำที่ต้นทางมาจากภาษาเดียวกันยังใช้คนละระบบในการถอดอักษรซะงั้น ที่เหนือกว่านั้นคือคำที่มาจาก บาลี-สันสกฤต นี่ก็ดันใช้ทั้งสองระบบถอดเสียงดื้อๆ โดยที่ไม่แคร์ว่าต่างชาติจะงงเบอร์ไหน</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FAQ</title>
      <link>/faq/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/faq/</guid>
      <description>How long do you have to eat gluten-free? Until the day I die. Or when I decide I want to die.
If you slowly increase your gluten intake you can eat bread in no time? In my case it&amp;rsquo;s an autoimmune disease, not allergy. Repeat after me: it&amp;rsquo;s not an allergy.
But you react to food? So how&amp;rsquo;s that not an allergy? Because I don&amp;rsquo;t get anaphylactic shock, and epi-pen can do nothing for me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Data engineer at a local startup. Usually works with godzilla-level data and machine learning infrastructure. Is a designated debugger at my office. Have a crush on Middle Eastern fiction and Turkish music. Language and history nerd. Symphonic metal is my jam.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Loanwords are okay</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-11-07-loanwords-are-okay/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-11-07-loanwords-are-okay/</guid>
      <description>Does it matter if you language has a lot of loanwords? To be considered a loan, it has to be of foreign origin, and speakers from the borrowing end can understand and use in various contexts. It&amp;rsquo;s perfectly okay for the meaning to shift on the borrowing end, as semantic shift happens naturally. It does not make the word &amp;ldquo;unpure&amp;rdquo; or anything, it&amp;rsquo;s just how things happen. The borrowing language may have different point of view or context, so not all properties from the source can be carried over.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indic name mistransliteration in Thai version of Harry Potter</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-10-11-indic-name-mistransliteration-in-thai-version-of-harry-potter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-10-11-indic-name-mistransliteration-in-thai-version-of-harry-potter/</guid>
      <description>I read Harry Potter as a kid, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t shake the feeling that one character&amp;rsquo;s name is a bit off. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite pinpoint exactly why. Turns out, my hunch was right – the Thai translator used the wrong transliteration.
In Thai, &amp;ldquo;Parvati Patil&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;ปาราวตี พาติล.&amp;rdquo; This doesn&amp;rsquo;t even match the English transliteration (from Indic), as seen by a completely messed up second syllable on the first name. Because Thai language has a lot of influences from Indic, we also have our own system of transliterating Indic to Thai.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Definition of &#39;a Word&#39;</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-07-31-definition-of-a-word/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-07-31-definition-of-a-word/</guid>
      <description>You often hear people say &amp;ldquo;you need to know x words in y language to be able to understand basic conversations.&amp;rdquo;. This is a bit misleading, since the definition of &amp;ldquo;word&amp;rdquo; is varied. For example, in Chinese (yes, I know, Chinese as a language doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, but I digress) one character (one block) is one word. So this is easy. Then you have Japanese, where the same kanji (Hanzi, Chinese characters) can be pronounced differently, each with different meaning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resettled refugees in Sweden</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-07-31-resettled-refugees-in-sweden/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-07-31-resettled-refugees-in-sweden/</guid>
      <description>One of my friends is a Syrian refugee, who was granted asylum in Sweden last year. I also want to try data analysis, so it fits that I should analyze something that&amp;rsquo;s relevant to my friend. This is my first ever analysis in pandas, apologies for code abomination in advance.
In this analysis, I use pandas for dataframe, numpy for dealing with numbers (because I need to count and do some math with it) and matplotlib for plotting graphs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How angur became องุ่น</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-11-24-how-angur-became-%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%B8%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%99/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-11-24-how-angur-became-%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%B8%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%99/</guid>
      <description>More often than not, Thai loanwords are of Indic, Khmer, English or Chinese origin. Although loans from other languages do exist. For instance, องุ่น (grape). This word is of Persian origin (read: Iran), which is انگور, literally angur. In Thai it&amp;rsquo;s angun. Notice that it&amp;rsquo;s n at the end instead of the original r. The reason is because in Thai r as end consonant doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, instead substituted with n. For example, the Sanskrit loanword ahar is pronounced as aha[n] in Thai.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The confusing case of Thai romanization system</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-09-15-the-confusing-case-of-thai-romanization-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-09-15-the-confusing-case-of-thai-romanization-system/</guid>
      <description>Thai Version
You decided to visit Thailand for whatever reason I don&amp;rsquo;t want to know. (It&amp;rsquo;s not my business.) Assuming you&amp;rsquo;re in from outside of Asia, you&amp;rsquo;ll land at Suvarnabhumi Airport. The problem? The locals don&amp;rsquo;t pronounce it that way. All the names and signs here are romanized using the Royal Thai General System of Transcription (RTGS). The big problem with this is that it is light years away of what Thais actually pronounce.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thailand is not really LGBT friendly</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-09-09-thailand-is-not-really-lgbt-friendly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-09-09-thailand-is-not-really-lgbt-friendly/</guid>
      <description>I just fished a documentary about the lives of LGBT people in China (and Hong Kong). One person from this documentary happened to be an elite in Hong Kong and he underwent sex reassignment surgery at a well-known clinic in Bangkok. She was very happy with the results and she relocated to Bangkok for however long, I don&amp;rsquo;t know. But what really got me thinking is the fact that she thought Thailand is more open to LGBT people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The curious case of why Thais ask where you study</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-09-08-the-curious-case-of-why-thais-ask-where-you-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-09-08-the-curious-case-of-why-thais-ask-where-you-study/</guid>
      <description>I was out for a stroll and I met a middle-aged person who, I think, knows my family. Without time being wasted, she asked &amp;ldquo;where do you study?&amp;rdquo; Where, not what.
Part of the reason why Thais ask &amp;ldquo;where&amp;rdquo; probably stems from the fact that they are a collective society, which means conformity and connections are very important. It&amp;rsquo;s safe to assume that people who went to the same school would &amp;ldquo;favor&amp;rdquo; people from their school when applying for jobs or asking for favors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Thais always ask when texting</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-09-06-what-thais-always-ask-when-texting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-09-06-what-thais-always-ask-when-texting/</guid>
      <description>These days all the IMs (instant messeging) have a) profile picture and b) name. Assuming these two are out of the question, Thais will always ask *:
* I know it’s a generalization but the percentage of Thais who do ask is far greater than those who don’t.
 Are you male or female? **
What is your age?
(Bonus question) Are you Thai?
** The conversation happened in English. Right away after saying hi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I no like English class</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-09-02-i-no-like-english-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-09-02-i-no-like-english-class/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this year I volunteered at an “English Clinic” at my school. The premise was to let students practice English with fluent speakers. Read: they don’t really want to practice English.
First day in, only one student there. Two of my friends were there so we together helped her correcting her written homework. Half way in I still spoke English with her but I sensed something wrong. As it turned out, she barely understood what I was saying, so I resorted to speaking to her in her native language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The state of Thai English texting group</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-08-30-the-state-of-thai-english-texting-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-08-30-the-state-of-thai-english-texting-group/</guid>
      <description>Most Thais can’t speak fluent English and this is a fact. But some like to pretend they can.
I found a member recruitment post so I said to myself “hey this looks interesting-ish this is great finally Thais will have more resources to learn English.” Instant disappointment.
The first group I was in was created by a Thai who wants to work in Europe. Her English? Mia Farang English — very broken English.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>