<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thai on Karn Wong</title>
    <link>kahnwong.github.io/tags/thai/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thai on Karn Wong</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="kahnwong.github.io/tags/thai/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ความน่าปวดหัวของการถอดอักษรไทยเป็นตัวโรมัน</title>
      <link>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2020-01-07-%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%9B%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%94%E0%B8%AB%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%82%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%96%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%94%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A9%E0%B8%A3%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%A2%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%9B%E0%B9%87%E0%B8%99%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%A7%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%99/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2020-01-07-%E0%B8%84%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%9B%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%94%E0%B8%AB%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%82%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%96%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%94%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%A9%E0%B8%A3%E0%B9%84%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%A2%E0%B9%80%E0%B8%9B%E0%B9%87%E0%B8%99%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%A7%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%A1%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%99/</guid>
      <description>English Version
*ตัวโรมัน = a b c d e f g &amp;hellip;
วันดีคืนดีชาวต่างชาติอยากมาเมืองไทย แต่จะมาเพราะอะไรนี่ก็ไม่ขอยุ่ง ไม่ได้สู่รู้เบอร์นั้น อนุมานว่ามาจากแถบยุโรป อเมริกาอะไรเทือกนี้ก็น่าจะเครื่องลงที่สุวรรณภูมิ ปัญหาที่จะเจออย่างแรกเลยก็คือ ชื่อป้ายชื่ออะไรไม่ได้ออกเสียงเหมือนที่ตัวโรมันเขียนไว้ เรื่องของเรื่องคือป้ายชื่อในไทยจะใช้ระบบ Royal Thai General System of Transcription ของ ราชบัณฑิตยสถาน แล้วปัญหาหลักๆ เลยก็คือมันไม่ได้สื่อว่าจริงๆ แล้วคำมันควรออกเสียงยังไง เช่น:
   Thai Romanization Romanization System Pronunciation Source     เทเวศ The-wet RTGS Tae-wet Pali-Sanskrit   สุวรรณภูมิ Suvarnabhumi Devanagari transliteration Su-wan*-na-poom *&amp;lsquo;a&amp;rsquo; as in father Pali-Sanskrit   ดินแดง Din-daeng RTGS Din-daeng Thai   ศรีราชา Sri Racha Mixed:__Sri__ - Devanagari transliteration__Racha__ - RTGS See-ra-cha Pali-Sanskrit    จะเห็นได้ว่าคำที่ต้นทางมาจากภาษาเดียวกันยังใช้คนละระบบในการถอดอักษรซะงั้น ที่เหนือกว่านั้นคือคำที่มาจาก บาลี-สันสกฤต นี่ก็ดันใช้ทั้งสองระบบถอดเสียงดื้อๆ โดยที่ไม่แคร์ว่าต่างชาติจะงงเบอร์ไหน</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indic name mistransliteration in Thai version of Harry Potter</title>
      <link>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2018-10-11-indic-name-mistransliteration-in-thai-version-of-harry-potter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2018-10-11-indic-name-mistransliteration-in-thai-version-of-harry-potter/</guid>
      <description>I read Harry Potter as a kid, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t shake the feeling that one character&amp;rsquo;s name is a bit off. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite pinpoint exactly why. Turns out, my hunch was right – the Thai translator used the wrong transliteration.
In Thai, &amp;ldquo;Parvati Patil&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;ปาราวตี พาติล.&amp;rdquo; This doesn&amp;rsquo;t even match the English transliteration (from Indic), as seen by a completely messed up second syllable on the first name. Because Thai language has a lot of influences from Indic, we also have our own system of transliterating Indic to Thai.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How angur became องุ่น</title>
      <link>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-11-24-how-angur-became-%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%B8%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%99/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-11-24-how-angur-became-%E0%B8%AD%E0%B8%87%E0%B8%B8%E0%B9%88%E0%B8%99/</guid>
      <description>More often than not, Thai loanwords are of Indic, Khmer, English or Chinese origin. Although loans from other languages do exist. For instance, องุ่น (grape). This word is of Persian origin (read: Iran), which is انگور, literally angur. In Thai it&amp;rsquo;s angun. Notice that it&amp;rsquo;s n at the end instead of the original r. The reason is because in Thai r as end consonant doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, instead substituted with n. For example, the Sanskrit loanword ahar is pronounced as aha[n] in Thai.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The confusing case of Thai romanization system</title>
      <link>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-09-15-the-confusing-case-of-thai-romanization-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-09-15-the-confusing-case-of-thai-romanization-system/</guid>
      <description>Thai Version
You decided to visit Thailand for whatever reason I don&amp;rsquo;t want to know. (It&amp;rsquo;s not my business.) Assuming you&amp;rsquo;re in from outside of Asia, you&amp;rsquo;ll land at Suvarnabhumi Airport. The problem? The locals don&amp;rsquo;t pronounce it that way. All the names and signs here are romanized using the Royal Thai General System of Transcription (RTGS). The big problem with this is that it is light years away of what Thais actually pronounce.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The curious case of why Thais ask where you study</title>
      <link>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-09-08-the-curious-case-of-why-thais-ask-where-you-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-09-08-the-curious-case-of-why-thais-ask-where-you-study/</guid>
      <description>I was out for a stroll and I met a middle-aged person who, I think, knows my family. Without time being wasted, she asked &amp;ldquo;where do you study?&amp;rdquo; Where, not what.
Part of the reason why Thais ask &amp;ldquo;where&amp;rdquo; probably stems from the fact that they are a collective society, which means conformity and connections are very important. It&amp;rsquo;s safe to assume that people who went to the same school would &amp;ldquo;favor&amp;rdquo; people from their school when applying for jobs or asking for favors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Thais always ask when texting</title>
      <link>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-09-06-what-thais-always-ask-when-texting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-09-06-what-thais-always-ask-when-texting/</guid>
      <description>These days all the IMs (instant messeging) have a) profile picture and b) name. Assuming these two are out of the question, Thais will always ask *:
* I know it’s a generalization but the percentage of Thais who do ask is far greater than those who don’t.
 Are you male or female? **
What is your age?
(Bonus question) Are you Thai?
** The conversation happened in English. Right away after saying hi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I no like English class</title>
      <link>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-09-02-i-no-like-english-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-09-02-i-no-like-english-class/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this year I volunteered at an “English Clinic” at my school. The premise was to let students practice English with fluent speakers. Read: they don’t really want to practice English.
First day in, only one student there. Two of my friends were there so we together helped her correcting her written homework. Half way in I still spoke English with her but I sensed something wrong. As it turned out, she barely understood what I was saying, so I resorted to speaking to her in her native language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The state of Thai English texting group</title>
      <link>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-08-30-the-state-of-thai-english-texting-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>kahnwong.github.io/posts/2017-08-30-the-state-of-thai-english-texting-group/</guid>
      <description>Most Thais can’t speak fluent English and this is a fact. But some like to pretend they can.
I found a member recruitment post so I said to myself “hey this looks interesting-ish this is great finally Thais will have more resources to learn English.” Instant disappointment.
The first group I was in was created by a Thai who wants to work in Europe. Her English? Mia Farang English — very broken English.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>